Guide to the Andrew St. George Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Original inventory, Accession 2010-M-036
  - Photographs
    - Cuba
      - Vilma Espín, Raúl and Fidel Castro, Osvaldo Dorticós, and Che Guevara, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 21)
        These photographs are images of major revolutionary leaders. Three show Fidel Castro: one with his head bowed sitting at table, Osvaldor Dorticós to Fidel's left, and Castro making the zero sign with his left hand. Others depict Raúl Castro giving a speech; Vilma Espín looking bored as she sits on a televised panel with a barely visible Lolo de la Torriente Brau, an aged but highly respected Cuban feminist, to her right; and finally, Raúl Castro with a pony tail and Che Guevara, smoking, with unidentified others who are applauding Fidel Castro wildly as he talks on the Ante La Prensa show.
      - Ernest Hemingway and Fidel at fishing tournament, 1959 May (Box 8, Folder 22)
        These images of Fidel Castro and Ernest Hemingway were taken at the latter's fishing tournament and regatta, May 1959. Similar and identical ones are also in Box 7, folder 19.
      - St. George's Spring trip to Cuban provinces with INRA Chiefs, Fidel Castro, René Vallejo and related excursions, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous photographs of buildings, unknown foreigners, street scenes, cars, and unidentified Cubans, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Fidel and other rebel officers speaking to crown on street at night, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - State visit of Soviet Vice Premier Anastas Mikoyan, 1960 February (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Fidel Castro (including one with his son, Fidel Castro Diaz-Balart) inside the home he shared with Celia Sánchez in El Vedado and directly in front of it, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Trial of José Sosa Blanco, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Fidel's caravan from Santiago to Havana, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Raúl Castro, radio address, and greeting loved ones and comrades, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - first days of January 1959, civilian leaders of 26th of July arrive in Camagüey airport; seen in other locations as they prepare to converge on Havana with Fidel, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Press conference at Havana Hilton19, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Woman who fainted from the heat at a mass rally to support revolutionary trials, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Roberto Agramonte and José Miró Cardona, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 12)
        Photographs of Roberto Agramonte, Revolutionary Government's 1st Minister of Foreign Relations, and José Miró Cardona, the Revolutionary Government's 1st Prime Minister. Miró Cardona resigned after only 6 weeks and was replaced by Fidel Castro.
      - Reception at Presidential Palace with Americans and Fidel Castro in attendance, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Vilma Espín and related images from the 1960 Anti-Imperialist Congress she attended in Mexico (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Cuban aide to Che Guevara giving speech on street in Lima, Peru, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Felipe Guerra Matos, 1959 January 1 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Fidel Castro on "Ante la Prensa," Cuban televised news show, 1959 October (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Miscellaneous images (duplicates) of early days of January 1959, 1959 January (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Personal photographs, different ages, images of same woman, apparently a Cuban who went into exile in May 1961, Circa 1949-1961 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Guerillas walking through village, Stokey carmichael, man working, Circa 1959-1967 (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - ASTA Convention October 1959, speech by Fidel, 1959 October (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Arrest of Fernando Vásquez by G2, Cuban intelligence forces, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - CTC Congress (Cuban Labor Confederation), 1960 March (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Unidentified American couple in a Cuban hotel; woman plays with a 26th of July Movement hand puppet, 1959 August (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Havana street life, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Peasants and rebels, 1958 October-December (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - I.D. of a Cuban State intelligence agent, Rafael Valera Perera, Circa 1958-1961 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        General
        The agency was called "DIER" as shown on the ID but it is commonly known as "G2".
      - Funeral procession for peasant killed by Batista forces, Oriente province, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - West German newspaper with front-page story on assassination of the West German ambassador in Guatemala, 1970 April (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Research memo 1970—assassination of West German Ambassador von Spreti and Cuban involvement (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Analysis of Guerrilla Warfare 1970 Article on Assassination of W. Ger. Amb. (Manuscript by StG), Circa 1970 (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Map of St. George's last trip to Sierra Maestra, October 21, 1958 to January 1959, Circa 1959 (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - NBC Radio transcript—Interview with St. George, Circa 1960 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Rebel forces take Caimanera, Holguín, Guantanamo and Batista forces surrender, 1959 January 1 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - First official press conference of new revolutionary government, 1959 January 23 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Fidel giving speech at Camp Columbia military base, 1960 March 30 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - First press conference, held in first week of January as Fidel's Caravan made its way to Havana, Circa 1959 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - William Morgan in profile, riding in a jeep; American member of Segundo Frente del Escambray, executed for treason, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - U.S./CIA-trained commando unit of exiles whom St. George accompanied on a mission to Cuba after the 1961 Bay of Pigs, Circa 1961 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - Peasants affiliated with 26th of July guerrilla column in Oriente, 1958 (Box 43, Folder 1)
        The peasants represented in these photographs are engaged in everyday activities such as winnowing corn, standing in line at a local dry goods store, and horseback riding. These peasants probably lived near the 26th of July columns commanded by Fidel and Raúl Castro. One image shows a typical hamlet of peasant homes in the plains region of Oriente, probably near Raúl Castro's column outside the highlands in a newly liberated zone when St. George visited his camp. Images date from Fall 1958.
      - Fidel Castro's tour of northeast U. S., 1959 April (Box 43, Folder 2)
        These photographs were taken during Fidel Castro's two-week tour of the northeast United States on invitation of the National Press Club. One photograph shows him sitting in a New York City hotel surrounded by 5 women. The notation by St. George on the back reads: "This unusual photo shows Fidel Castro with five women who played a significant romantic role in his life. From left to right: Conchita Fernández (no hat) in whose house he lived and who was his lady friend in Habana while Castro was finishing law school and beginning his political career; Tete Casuso (bangs, off-the-shoulder dress) in whose house he lived in romantic union during his year of exile in Mexico City in 1956; Isabela Montero, a fashionable Havana divorcee who was frequently seen with Castro in 1960; Celia Sánchez, with whom he lived and who served as his principal courier during the two years of jungle guerrilla warfare (1957-1958); and Nora Serrano, a Havana journalist, who often stayed overnight with Castro in the Habana Hilton in 1961-62 (wide-brimmed white hat)." The photograph of Castro responding to reporters questions with his translator Tete Casuso at his side includes this caption: "Seated next to Castro (right) is Tete Casuso, who was his paramour and in whose house Castro lived during his year of exile in Mexico. After rebel victory in Habana, Mme. Casuso was rewarded with post of Castro's personal Pressechef and she traveled everywhere with Fidel. But fierce jealousies and deadly intrigues among ladies of what Mme. Casuso used to call 'Fidel's harem' – Celia Sanchez, Conchita Fernandez, other, younger women – drove Mme. Casuso into exile in the mid-Sixties. She now lives in France." Additional photographs show Fidel after placing a floral wreath at the foot of the Jefferson Memorial in Washington, DC; giving a speech to the American Society of Newspaper Editors at the Statler Hilton in New York with Tete Casuso gazing at Castro; making a televised appearance on NBC's "Meet the Press" on April 19, 1959, with the show's moderator Ned Brooks and interpreter Anthony Hervas (an identical photograph is in Box 8, folder 7); and giving an interview to an unidentified reporter.
      - Fidel's visit to New York, 1960 September (Box 43, Folder 3)
        These photographs document Fidel Castro and his delegation's September 1960 visit to New York City to attend a meeting at the United Nations where Fidel gave his famous speech announcing the upcoming Literacy Campaign of 1961. The Cuban delegates ultimately stayed at the Hotel Theresa in Harlem after a dispute with a Manhattan hotel. One photograph shows African American supporters demonstrating in Harlem and fighting off police; hand-held signs read "US Jim Crows Fidel Just Like US Jim Crows Us Negroes!" and "Fidel is Welcome in Harlem Anytime!". Additional images show the police escort standing before the entrance to the Hotel Theresa; Fidel and Juan Almeida enjoying a dinner with the hotel staff before a mob of reporters at the hotel; Almeida talking to two waitresses at a nearby coffee shop; Almeida and other Cuban delegates, including Antonio Nuñez Jiménez, standing at the counter of the same coffee shop, apparently listening to someone or watching a televised broadcast; crowds of supporters standing before the windows of the hotel; members of the delegation looking down at them; and of a demonstration against Castro where protesters stood behind a barricade holding a large poster image of image of Camilo Cienfuegos and signs comparing Fidel to Hitler. In the foreground, next to a shouting demonstrator wearing a hand-painted T-shirt reading 'Cuba SI' (in English, Cuba Yes) is Luis Conte Agüero. Conte Agüero had been Castro's close friend and informal public relations manager during his imprisonment on the Isle of Pines under Batista from 1953 to 1955. Conte Agüero left Cuba in 1960; at the time, he was a journalist and television personality. An identical photograph is in Box 8, folder 7.
      - Havana airport: Faure Chomón and top Cuban Communist Carlos Rafael Rodríguez, 1960 February (Box 43, Folder 4)
        The nearly identical photographs show Faure Chomón (wearing dark jacket and dark shirt), former member of the Student Directorate that fought the Batista dictatorship, and Carlos Rafael Rodríguez (wearing sport coat and horizontal stripe tie) (later President of INRA in 1963, then Fidel's Deputy Prime Minister from 1970s to 1980s), long-time ideologue of the Cuban Communist Party (known as the Partido Socialista Popular) and editor of its organ, Hoy. Chomón and Rodríguez are answering a reporter's questions at the Havana airport as they await the arrival of Vice Premier Anastas Mikoyan.
      - Soviet Vice Premier Anastas Mikoyan visit to Havana, 1960 February (Box 43, Folder 5)
        These images document the visit of Vice Premier Anastas Mikoyan to Cuba in February 1960. Ostensibly, Mikoyan was there to inaugurate the traveling exhibit of Soviet culture and products that would be held at the Museo de Bellas Artes in Havana. Also included are photographs of a student protest held in Central Park shortly after Mikoyan deposited an imperial-looking floral wreath with Soviet bloc symbols at the foot of the monument to Cuban nationalist leader José Martí. Other images show the lavish state reception Prime Minister Fidel Castro and President Osvaldo Dorticós held at the Presidential Palace to honor Mikoyan on the day of his arrival; Mikoyan at the airport; and members of the Soviet security detail as they kept watch during the reception at the Presidential Palace. One of the photographs is from an issue of Life magazine.
      - Roadblocks strike to support government, 1959 October (Box 43, Folder 6)
        These images show young Cuban men participating in roadblocks, probably as part of a public strike in support of the Cuban government in October 1959. Two prints are of roadblocks on the Malecón, the sea wall that borders Havana's northern shore, and one is of a road block on Calle Línea, Vedado.
      - Hotel Nacional, Winter 1960, top gun/weapons dealer photographed in reception area (Box 43, Folder 7)
        These prints document the presence of American arms dealer Col. Hubert F. Julian in Havana; in each he is seen with an unidentified woman from Virginia and holding a check to be cashed at Havana's Nacional Hotel. There are related images in the Cuban Revolution Collection (MS 650, http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/mssa.ms.0650, see Book IV Print 29: Arms dealer Col. Hubert F. Julian) in which St. George describes more fully Julian's presence in Cuba.
      - Visiting Chinese delegates emerging from the Presidential Palace, 1960 (Box 43, Folder 8)
        This photograph is of a visiting Chinese delegation emerging from the Presidential Palace, probably mid- to late-1960. It is captioned as follows: "Che's Chinese allies, arriving in Habana by the planeload, included many military instructors and 'political workers' in civilian dress. Fanatic commitment to guerrilla warfare and constant hostility to US united Che and Chinese leaders: Che believes (and has led Fidel Castro to believe for a while) that if national frontiers are disregarded, Latin America is very much like pre-revolutionary China, huge, starving, agrarian, vulnerable to the same peasant guerrilla strategy which brought Communists victory in China."
      - School boys at the newly constructed school at the former Moncada military barracks in Oriente, 1960 (Box 43, Folder 9)
        These images are of young school boys during morning assembly at the newly constructed school at the former Moncada military barracks in Oriente. It was at this barracks that Fidel's ill-prepared armed force attacked on the 26th of July 1953, resulting in a massacre of most of its members. Fidel's subsequent guerrilla movement took the 26th of July as its name in honor of the dead and wounded from that famous attack. Although Fidel claimed that he would convert military barracks into schools, that conversion ironically entailed the creation of highly militarized schools such as this one. These photographs show the boys carrying their metal trays for breakfast and assembling to march, military-style, into the dining area. At this time, many of these boys would likely have come from poor, marginal families near the Sierra Maestra. This explains their disheveled appearance and the fact that at least one of them (a black boy) is not wearing shoes. One photograph is captioned: "II. MILITARY FEVER GRIPS CUBA. Barracks-type drill discipline is applied to all but the youngest children in Castro's Cuba. Here peasant boys recruited from the Sierra Maestra region are shown in front of a school center, partly completed (right) but largely still under construction (left and right rear.) This school center, a surprisingly large and modern construction project among the roadless Sierra Maestra foothills (the nearest settlement is tiny El Cerro, and the nearest town of any size, Manzanillo, is a hundred miles away) will eventually house 20,000 farm children. The boys shown here, part of the first contingent of 500 already living and studying at the school center, spend their day under supervision of Cuban rebel army drill instructors, and - under Communist Chinese pattern the Cuban Army appears to be imposing on rural education - only half their day is spent in school; half is spent in work out among the canebrakes."
      - Unidentified American man at his trial for counter-revolutionary activities, Circa 1960 (Box 43, Folder 10)
        In this series of photographs, an unidentified American man is shown at his trial for counter-revolutionary activities, probably in 1960. He is under heavy armed guard at the trial in one image and is seen with expressions of anger and defiance as he listens to the proceedings. The trial was conducted by Revolutionary Tribunal and probably resulted in the man's execution or long-term imprisonment.
      - Fidel Castro and personal "secretary" Celia Sánchez Manduley with body guards and small crowd, Nuevo Vedado, Havana, 1959 (Box 43, Folder 11)
        This photograph is of Fidel Castro and his personal secretary (often considered his common-law wife) Celia Sánchez, surrounded by his personal body guards as he prepares to enter a car on a street in Vedado. They are most likely standing in front of Sánchez's apartment, which Fidel considered home during the early years of the Revolution. Sánchez is shown in profile holding some newspapers.
      - Surveillance photographs, counter-revolutionary violence, police checkpoints, and militarization of Cuba prior to Bay of Pigs invasion, 1960 (Box 43, Folder 12)
        In this series of photographs St. George appears to document the surge in security measures taken by the Cuban government in 1960 as it mobilized to defend against the U.S. invasion at the Bay of Pigs in April 1961. The photographs show snipers posted on the roof of Havana's airport; a wrecked train and a burned-out bus that appear to have been the products of counter-revolutionary assaults; a plane of the type manned by exile counter-revolutionary forces in their regular invasions of Cuban airspace (this one appears to have either crash landed or been shot down by Cuban defenses); and images of a police check point on the western outskirts of Havana near the San Alejandro Art Academy.
      - Accompanying René Vallejo and Fidel Castro on inspection of rural projects, 1960 January (Box 43, Folder 13)
        Dating from the early months of 1960, these photographs were taken when St. George accompanied Fidel Castro and Antonio Nuñez Jiménez, both directors of Instituto Nacional de Reforma Agraria (INRA), as they made an inspection tour of recently nationalized farms and plantations in the interior of the country. The images include a shot of several university-age students outfitted in militia uniforms as they await the arrival of a bus that will probably take them to a political education camp in the mountains. The students wear new boots and are carrying weapons as well as personal items, including multiple packs of cigarettes in the case of the boy and a fashionable fur hat in the case of one of the girls. Another image shows Fidel and his aide René Vallejo surrounded by peasants in a small town. Additional images show Fidel walking along a road at a state farm with others; Fidel addressing a group of peasants at the state farm's social club for workers (volleyball net in foreground, Fidel's head barely visible above the crowd); a young peasant with a rifle doing guard duty before the INRA Tienda del Pueblo; INRA officials in a corn field; Vallejo talking with officials at the foot of a ceiba tree; an unidentified construction site; peasants lounging on a tractor as the sun sets in the background; peasant driving an ox cart; Vallejo reviewing correspondence in a hotel room; and peasants on a cart in front of the Tienda del Pueblo.
      - Radicalization process, including state control over the press, public spaces, and political indoctrination of programs, 1960 (Box 43, Folder 14)
        The radicalization process of 1960 and the participation of the population in various state programs of political indoctrination and economic management were modeled on the Soviet and Chinese Communist system. These photographs include a shot of a political education class in which all participants wear the uniform of the Revolutionary Militia; a rally before the Presidential Palace, shot from the balcony or its roof; young girls marching military-style under the supervision of drill instructors on San Lázaro Street, a main artery that connects the University of Havana with Centro Habana; Fidel and other officials gathered at the monument to José Martí in Revolutionary Plaza, minutes before a major rally; hand-made signs posted on the storefront of Western Union on Havana's Obispo Street, protesting the closure of the office and the firing of Cuban employees; a wide-angle street scene taken on Carlos III, a wide avenue in Havana, showing the nationalist political postings on the median and wall of a building (these claim revolutionary goals as "National Sovereignty, Economic Independence, Agrarian Reform, Industrialization"); a newsstand featuring only government-controlled media and magazines from socialist countries; a government print shop with political propaganda books published recently; men suiting up for militia duty (duplicate print is in Box 8, folder 4); and a wall with graffiti supporting Fidel. The image of the girls marching includes a strip caption on back by St. George that reads "In typical tableau, group of 6-8 year old schoolgirls [sic] drill under 2 rebel army instructors on Havana's central San Lazaro St." The photograph with Fidel and other leaders assembled on the speaker's platform at the monument to Martí includes notes on the back that correspond to numbers St. George penciled in, pinpointing certain figures standing with Fidel. They are American William Morgan (later shot for treason in 1961), Eloy Gutiérrez Menoyo (later founder of the exile guerrilla Alpha 66) and Aubelz (?). St George seems to be indicating who were members of the Segundo Frente Escambray, an independent guerrilla organization that allied with Fidel's movement to topple Batista. After 1960, the Segundo Frente's members became suspect because they were all avowedly anti-Communist and therefore believed to be tied to the CIA. The photograph of the men suiting up for military duty includes this caption: II: MILITARY FEVER GRIPS CUBA / With all Cubans (of both sexes) between the ages of 6 and 60 eligible for milicia duty, and with new anti-Castro guerrilla forces fighting in the mountains of the Sierra Maestra (mountains in the background) all Cuba is getting into uniform, like these shivering and reluctant milicianos of the Havana Architects' and Lawyers Militia Battalion: they are called to duty to defend the government against anti-Castro "bandits" (who have entered violent battle against the Castro regime during first weeks of April) and against a "foreign invasion" which has not yet materialized, but which Castro seems to expect. This photo was taken in brand-new – as yet unfinished – militia camp at Las Mercedes, among Sierra Maestra foothills.
      - Lima, Peru, 1965 (Box 43, Folder 15)
        These identical prints of a Cuban named Luis Uceda de la Fuente, giving a speech at a street rally in Lima, Peru, 1964. One of the images contains a caption: Che's close friend and ally Luis Uceda de la Fuente harangues Lima street crowd under typical poster showing US as rat spitted by Cuban machete. Luis Uceda was sent to the Andes mountains last year by Che to take charge of guerrilla offensive: he was killed by US-trained Peruvian antiguerrilla [sic] troops in December, 1965." Part of a number of photographs St. George put together to retrace and identify Che Guevara's plan to export revolution to South America
      - Vilma Espín's Conference of Latin American Left, Mexico City, 1960 (Box 43, Folder 16)